Finding Aid for Ruth Bordin papers, 1940-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ruth Bordin papers 1940-1992, 1980-1992
Bordin, Ruth Birgitta Anderson, 1917-
1 linear feet
8890 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, historian and writer. Manuscripts of writings and papers presented at professional organizations; topics of research include Emma Hall, Michigan prison reformer, the Woman's Christian Temperance Union, Frances Willard, Alice Freeman Palmer, women's history, and Washtenaw County, Michigan; also photographs and sound recordings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was a gift of Ruth Bordin to the University of Michigan (Donor No. 3384 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ruth Bordin was born in Litchfield, Minnesota on November 11, 1917. She received both her B.A.(1938) and M.A.(1941) from the University of Minnesota. She married Edward Bordin in 1941 and devoted the next several years of her life to raising a family. Bordin became professionally active again when she took on the position of curator of manuscripts at the Michigan Historical Collection in 1957. She left in 1967 when she joined the history faculty at Eastern Michigan University, which position she held until 1979. From 1980 until her death, Bordin returned to the Michigan Historical Collections (now the Bentley Historical Library) as a research affiliate where she was responsible for a number of special projects and exhibits, notably the "Nancy and G. Mennen Williams Oral History Project" and "Promise and Performance," an extensive exhibit commemorating the 50th anniversary of the Michigan Historical Collections in 1985.
Bordin was a prolific historian and writer. In 1966, she prepared a Pictorial History of the University of Michigan. In the 1980s, she began specializing in women's history writing biographies of Frances Willard and Alice Freeman Palmer and a monograph on the women of the temperance movement. Professionally active, Bordin was a member of the Organization of American Historians and the Women Historian's Organization of the Midwest. She attended meetings of this organizations, often presenting papers or serving as a commentator. Ruth Bordin died in 1994.
The Ruth Bordin Papers have been divided into five series: Biographical/personal, Writings, Topical Files, Photographs, and Sound Recordings.
The Writings series consists of copies of unpublished conference papers and published books reviews and articles. The bulk of the collection has been arranged into a Topical File and consists of correspondence and other materials arranged alphabetically, either by subject or by name of correspondent. The other three series are small and are described as part of the container listing.
Subjects:
Hall, Emma Amelia, 1837-1884.; Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1855-1902.; Willard, Frances E. (Frances Elizabeth), 1839-1898.; Women--United States--History.; Woman's Christian Temperance Union.; Washtenaw County (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dwellings--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Interiors.; Spencer House (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Dwellings.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Bordin, Ruth Birgitta Anderson, 1917-; University of Michigan. Center for Continuing Education of Women.; Women--Education, Higher--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Cain, Louise G.; Campbell, Jean.; Likert, Jane Gibson.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical/personal
  - Vita, college grades, letters of application, etc. (Box 1)
- Writings (Conference papers, articles, etc.)
  - 1980 "Emma Hall and the management of public institutions", 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - 1981, "Upon this rock; Women's church networks and the mass organization of women into the WCTU, 1873-1883" (Box 1)
  - 1982, "Coopting the private sphere; Women and institutional management in the nineteenth century" (Box 1)
  - 1983, "Frances Willard and the practice of political influence" (Box 1)
  - 1988, "An impassioned sisterhood; The transatlantic community of temperance and peace, 1870-1920" (Box 1)
  - Student papers 1940, undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Conference papers (also informal talks) (Box 1)
  - Book reviews (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous writings (Box 1)
- Topical files
  (mainly correspondence, but including some clippings; also includes files with individual correspondents)
  - Articles and conference papers (correspondence about)
    - "A Baptism of Power and Liberty..." December 1977-October 1983 (Box 1)
    - "Coopting the Private Sphere..." May 1982-August 1989 (Box 1)
  - Berkshire Conferences 1981-1983, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Beveridge Grant January 1982-December 1983 (Box 1)
  - Blocker, Jack (Box 1)
  - Brumberg, Joan Jacobs (Box 1)
  - Buhle, Mari Jo (Box 1)
  - Center for Continuing Education of Women Symposium 1987 ("Change in the lives of educated women") (Box 1)
  - Conference on the History of Women 1981 (Box 1)
  - Detroit Institute of Art 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - "Encyclopedia of Religion in the South," September 1982-April 1986 (Box 1)
  - English research 1982-1989 (Box 1)
  - Female Sphere Conference 1983 (Box 1)
  - Frederick Ungar Publishing Co. (American Women Writers) (Box 1)
  - Giele, Janet Zollinger (Box 1)
  - Hall (Emma) manuscript (correspondence about) (Box 1)
  - Michigan Women's Hall of Fame (Box 1)
  - National Women's Christian Temperance Union (Box 1)
  - Nez Perce book 1986 (Box 1)
  - Organization of American Historians meeting 1983 (Box 1)
  - Palmer (Alice Freeman) biography research correspondence, etc., 3 folders (Box 1)
  - National Women's Hall of Fame (Box 1)
  - Papachristou, Judy (Box 1)
  - Penn State University (Box 1)
  - Pugh, Mary Jo (Box 1)
  - Research Guide to American History (Box 1)
  - Scott, Anne Firor (Box 1)
  - SIGNS (Journal of Women in Culture and Society), September 1983-April 1986 (Box 1)
  - Sklar, Kathryn Kish (Box 1)
  - Smith College Summer Workshop 1983 (Box 1)
  - Turner Clinic Project 1990 (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw County history (correspondence about research and publication of volume) (Box 1)
  - Willard (Frances) biography research correspondence, etc., 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Willard (Frances) biography (reviews of manuscript and of book) (Box 1)
  - Women and temperance, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Women in the New World conference 1980 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Copyprints used in her various publications, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Sound cassettes
  - Interviews with Louise Cain, Jean Campbell, and Jane Likert regarding the history of the U-M Center for Continuing Education of Women 1985 (Box 1)